Guide to the Albert Jay Nock Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- PAUL PALMER, 1911-1945, 1946; Series II; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  - Writings
    - Letter to the editor of The World, from Albert Jay Nock, [re:] the Philharmonic Orchestra, January 14, (1925?). (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - "Mayor Gaynor's Letters," (by A. J. Nock?); Galley Proofs (from The American Magazine ?) (July 12, 1912?). (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - "A Premium on Tax Lying," by A. J. Nock; undated, periodical unknown. (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Review by A. J. Nock of "Out of the Night," by Jan Valtin, in Scribner's Commentator, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Review by A. J. Nock of The State in Theory and Practice, by Harold J. Laski; in The Atlantic Monthly. (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - "The Second Empire," by A. J. Nock, from Analysis, August, 1945. (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - A published article [re:] travel across Canada by rail (by A. J. Nock?), undated periodical unknown (order of pages uncertain). (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - "World Scouts," by A. J. Nock from The American Magazine, pp. 275-284, undated. (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Printed Matter
    - Articles mentioning A. J. Nock. (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Dust jackets for Letters From Albert Jay Nock and A Journey Into Rabelais's France, by Albert Jay Nock. (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - In Perspective, "Who Reads What?" by "G.A.B. from the Providence, Rhode Island Journal, undated, [re:] Nock's statement in Encore that he read no periodicals save Encore. (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - Newspaper clippings [re:] "American Indifference to Affairs of Government…" by A. J. Nock. (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Newspaper clippings on A Journey into Rabelais's France, empnasizing Ruth Robinson's pen and ink drawings. (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Brief newspaper clippings mentioning or quoting Albert Jay Nock. (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Obituary notices for A. J. Nock. (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Photographs of A. J. Nock. (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - Reviews of Nock's books. (Box 7, Folder 78)
- ROBERT M. CRUNDEN, 1892, 1911-1945, 1955-1964; Series III; 5" (1 box)
  This series contains material collected by Robert M. Crunden for an undergraduate thesis at Yale University, which he later published as a book, The Mind and Art of Albert Jay Nock (Chicago: Henry Regnery Co., 1964). The series consists of three subsections: "Correspondence," "Writings," and "Special Files."
  "Correspondence" includes copies of letters or excerpts from letters written by Nock to various people and one letter to Nock from Ellery Sedgwick. The originals of these letters are in the possession of Francis Jay and Samuel Albert Nock. The balance of this section consists of replies to Crunden's requests for information from people who knew Nock. The copies of Nock's correspondence are arranged alphabetically by the name of the recipient (except for the Sedgwick letter); the Crunden correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the writer of the letter.
  "Writings" consists of materials both by and about Nock. Writings by Nock include published articles, a manuscript autobiographical sketch Nock wrote for Paul Palmer, an unpublished manuscript journal of Nock's travels in Europe in 1935, three short stories (only one of which has been published), and the commencement address which Nock delivered at his graduation from St. Stephen's College in 1892. These are followed by writings about Nock, which are arranged alphabetically by author. Anonymous articles and all of the reviews are at the end of this section. Of special interest are the biographical sketches of Nock by Paul Palmer and Ruth Robinson.
  "Special Files" contains printed materials not directly related to Nock and miscellaneous notes written by Ruth Robinson after Nock's death.
  - Correspondence
    - Bell, Bernard Iddings (from Nock), 1933, 1934, 1943, undated copies. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Gipson, James H. (from Nock), November 29, 1944(?), copy. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Lange, Elizabeth (from Nock), October 17, 1943, copy.' (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Kirk, Russell (from Nock), July 9, 1945, copy. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Lichtenstein, Walter (from Nock), June 5, 1944, copy. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Mencken, H. L. (from Nock), March 16, 1921, copy. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Nock, Samuel A. (from A. J. Nock), (June 17, 1941?] Copy. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Oliva, Felix M. (from Nock), May 16, 1944, copy. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Robinson, Ruth (from Nock), January 1, 1938, copy. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Sedgwick, Ellery (to Nock), February 26, 1930, copy. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - The American Journal of Economics and Sociology. (Box 8, Folder 11)
      See also: box 8, folder 38
    - Aring, Charles D. to Crunden, 1963. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Arvin, Newton to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Bard College (formerly St. Stephen's College), 1961, 1962, to Crunden. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Barnes, Harry Elmer to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Barzun, Jacques (provost, Columbia University) to Crunden, 1961, 1964. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Bean, William B. to Crunden, 1963. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Berkeley Divinity School, 1962, to Crunden. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Bigelow, Paul to Crunden, 1961, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Broadhurst, E. H. to Crunden, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Chamberlin, William Henry to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Chodorov, Frank to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Christ Episcopal Church, Blacksburg, Virginia. (Box 8, Folder 23)
      See also: box 8, folder 55
    - Columbia University. (Box 8, Folder 24)
      See also: box 8, folder 16
    - Cziraky, Sandor to Crunden, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - DosPassos, John to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Eastman, Max to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Fischer, Hanns to Crunden, 1963. (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Foundation for Economic Education, Inc. (Box 8, Folder 29)
      See also: box 8, folder 44
    - Garrison, Eleanor to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Grierson, Margaret Storrs (Sophia Smith Collection--Smith College Library), 1961, to Crunden. (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Hazo, Robert G. to Crunden (Institute for Philosophical Research), 1962, 1963. (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Hillyer, Robert to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Huebsch, B. W. to Crunden (The Viking Press, Inc.), 1961. (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Institute for Philosophical Research. (Box 8, Folder 35)
      See also: box 8, folder 32
    - LaFollette, Suzanne to Crunden, 1961, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Library of Congress (David C. Mearns, chief, MS. Division) to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Lissner, Will to Crunden ( The American Journal of Economics and Sociology ), 1961. (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - MacCarran (?), Hugh, to Crunden, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Mearns, David C. (Box 8, Folder 40)
      See also: box 8, folder 37
    - Mumford, Lewis, to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Nock, Francis Jay to Crunden, 1951 (1961?), 1961, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Nock, Samuel Albert to Crunden, 1961, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Opitz, Edmund A.(Foundation for Economic Education, Inc.) to Crunden, 1961, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Palmer, Paul to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Perkins, Frances to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Peterson, V. G. (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Robinson, Geroid T. to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Robinson, Ruth to Crunden, 1961-1964 and undated. (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - St. Stephen's College. (Box 8, Folder 50)
      See also: box 8, folder 14
    - Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College Library. (Box 8, Folder 51)
      See also: box 8, folder 31
    - Tachau, William G. to Crunden, undated. (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Turner, Susan J. to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Van Doren, Mark from/to Crunden, 1961. (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Walke, Roger A. Jr., Rector (Christ Episcopal Church, Blacksburg, Va.) 1962, to Crunden. (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - Wesleyan University to Crunden, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - Wilson, Catherine R. to Crunden, 1962. (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Writings
    - Autobiographical sketch of A. J. Nock written for Paul Paul Palmer. Copy of the original (which is in the Palmer Series), in the handwriting of Nock. (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Autobiographical sketch of A. J. Nock, written for Paul Palmer. Typed copy of the original (which is in the Palmer, Series). (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - "Democracy Here and Abroad," by A. J. Nock, copied from the New York Evening Post, January 30, 1918. (Two copies.) (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - Fists Across the Sea--an Unsentimental Prophecy, by A. J. Nock in Harper's Monthly Magazine vol. 154, Feb. 1927, pp. 274-280. (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - "Introduction," by Albert J. Nock to Meditations in Wall Street, Anonymous, December 1, 1939. (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - "Introduction," by Albert J. Nock; book and author unknown, September 30, 1915. (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - "Introduction to the Fourth Edition," by Albert Jay Nock; book and author unknown, October 13, 1921. (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - "Introduction," by Albert Jay Nock; book, author, and date unknown. (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Mr. Smith and Mr. Smythe--The Real Causes of British-American Friction, by A. J. Nock in Harper's Monthly Magazine, pp. 691-697, undated. (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - "To Paul Palmer," notes concerning three natural laws, by A. J. Nock, August 1, 1944. (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - "To Paul Palmer," notes re: the meaning of "liberalism," by A. J. Nock. October 30, 1944. (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Short story--"A Puritan Heart," by "Cav. A de Angelis" (A. J. Nock), July, 1911, (published in American Magazine, May 19, 1912). (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Short story--"An Influence," by "Cav. Angelo de Angelis" (A. J. Nock), unpublished. (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Short story--"A Tatiana of the South," by "Cav. Angelo de Angelis" (A. J. Nock), unpublished. (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - "What Has My Education Done For Me?" by A. J. Nock; a commencement address delivered June 16, 1892, at St. Stephen's College (Nock was in class of 1892 at St. Stephen's). (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Chamberlain, John, "A.J. N./Man of Letters," in A Reviewer's Notebook, in The Freeman, November, 1962, pp. 59-62. (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Chodorov, Frank, "Gentle Nock at Our Door," in Faith and Freedom, February, 1955. (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Palmer, Paul, "Palmer Sketch," of A. J. Nock; undated, after Nock's death. (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark; article mentioning A. J. Nock (title missing) from the New York Times Book Review, June 9, 1963. (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Reed, John, The Day in Bohemia, or, Life Among the Artists, two excerpts mentioning Nock, 1913. (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Robinson, Ruth; memories of Albert Jay Nock as she wrote them (for use in Selected Letters of Albert Jay Nock ). (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Robinson, Ruth; memories of Albert Jay Nock, as revised by Paul Bigelow (for use in Selected Letters of Albert Jay Nock ). (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Anonymous--History of A. J. Nock's career at St. James Church; anonymous, untitled, undated. (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - "The Freeman," Chapter IV of ? by ? (Literary Editor of the Freeman) (contains information about Nock), date, author, and source unknown. (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - "The Nockian Society," a newsletter announcing tentative formation of the Society, February 14, 1963. (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Reviews of Nock's books. (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Special Files
    - Advertisement and order form for Selected Letters of Albert Jay Nock from Caxton Printers, Ltd. (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Newspaper clippings on: 1. fire at the Player's Club; 2. death of Van Wyck Brooks. (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Nock, Samuel Albert, "Editorial Comment," obituary for H. L. Mencken, spring, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Robinson, Ruth, "Memo for Biographical First Chapter," (corrective notes and suggestions--for Crunden's book?). (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Robinson, Ruth; copy or draft of letter to Francis Jay Nock, undated. (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - von Harringa, Ernest, "Quotations from letters from Ernest von Harringa to R.R. (Ruth Robinson)", in the handwriting of Ruth Robinson, 1958, 1959. (Box 8, Folder 89)